Guide to the Patricia Murphy Derian Papers, 1962-2008 and undated RL.00305
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Patricia Murphy Derian papers
1962-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Derian, Patricia M.
RL.00305
15.3 Linear Feet
Patricia Murphy Derian is an activist, organizer, researcher, and served as the first Assistant Secretary of State for Human Rights (HR) and Humanitarian Affairs (HA), a bureau of the executive branch created in 1977 during the Carter Administration. The papers of Patricia M. Derian cover the years 1962-2007 and document Derian's involvement and interventions concerning international human rights, and to a lesser extent, civil liberties and women's rights. The collection comprises Derian's personal notes; correspondence with state officials, friends and human rights activists; unclassified State Department documents; reports; interviews; memorabilia; and news clippings. These and other materials provide valuable insights to the history of human rights activism and major cases of human rights violations from the early 1970s up to the second term of the George W. Bush administration. The scope of Derian's papers is extensive, covering the history of human rights movements and national policies and politics since the early 1970s in Asia, the Middle East, and Latin America. Topics include U.S. foreign and military policies, repercussions of those policies, and disappearances, torture and other forms of violation of human rights. Derian's papers include subject files on Argentina, El Salvador, Chile, Cuba, Guatemala, Honduras, Nicaragua, Paraguay, South Korea, Vietnam, and Middle Eastern countries, as well as smaller files on sixteen other countries. Many of these country files cover several decades of information and analysis. Especially significant are documents concerning U.S.-El Salvador and U.S.-Argentina relations during the 1970s and 1980s. Other topics in the collection include women's rights, women in public office, and civil rights movements in the U.S., especially in Mississippi. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Approximately 10,175 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Patricia Murphy Derian Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Biographical Note
Patricia Murphy Derian was born in New York City in 1929 and and grew up in Virginia, where she received a degree from the University of Virginia School of Nursing in 1952. She is a former Secretary for Human Rights, a veteran of the Civil Rights movement, and an international human rights activist. In early years she acted as consultant to the Office of Economic Opportunity for the oversight of the Mississippi Action for Progress (MAP). She served as Deputy Director for Jimmy Carter's presidential 1980 campaign. She became the first Secretary of Human Rights when Carter formed the State Department's Bureau for Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs in 1977. During that period she wrote Human Rights: A World Perspective (1978), Human Rights in Latin America (1979), Human Rights in Jeopardy (1980), and Review of Human Rights in Latin America (1980). Since leaving the U.S. government in 1981, she has continued to work as a human rights activist with a number of non-profit organizations. She is married to Hodding Carter III, former Assistant Secretary of State for Public Affairs under President Carter.
Collection Overview
The Patricia Murphy Derian papers cover the years 1962-2008 and document Derian's involvement and interventions concerning human rights and civil liberties in the U.S. and worldwide. Derian was an activist, organizer, researcher, and served as the first Assistant Secretary of State for Bureau for Human Rights (HR) and Humanitarian Affairs (HA), created in 1977 by President Jimmy Carter. The collection comprises Derian's personal notes; correspondence with state officials, friends and human rights activists; unclassified State Department documents; reports; travel information; posters (located in the Oversize Material); interviews (both audio-visual and printed); memorabilia; and news clippings. These and other materials provide valuable insights into the history of human rights activism and major cases of human rights violations from the early 1970s up to the second term of the George W. Bush administration. The collection is arranged into five series: Carter Administration - 1980 Campaign and Employment, Department of State Human Rights (HR) and Humanitarian Affairs (HA) Bureau, Post-Carter Administration Human Rights Work, Countries, and Audiovisual Material. A final group houses oversize material. The scope of Derian's papers is extensive, covering the history of human rights movements and national policies and politics since the early 1970s in Asia, the Middle East, and Latin America. U.S. foreign and military policies, repercussions of those policies, and documentation of disappearances, torture and other forms of violation of human rights are documented extensively in the Department of State Human Rights (HR) and Humanitarian Affairs (HA) Bureau Series, and in the large Countries Series, which brings together Derian's files on Argentina, El Salvador, Chile, Cuba, Guatemala, Honduras, Nicaragua, Paraguay, South Korea, Vietnam, and Middle Eastern countries, as well as a grouping on sixteen other countries. Many of these country files cover several decades of information and analysis. Especially significant are documents concerning U.S.-El Salvador and U.S.-Argentina relations during the 1970s and 1980s. Other topics in the collection include women's rights, women in public office, civil liberties in the U.S., and the human rights work of foundations such as the Carter-Menil Human Rights Foundation and Robert F. Kennedy Memorial Foundation.
The Carter Administration - 1980 Carter-Mondale Campaign and Employment series includes materials concerning the organization of the 1980 Carter-Mondale election campaign; it also documents employment procedures for Derian's position at the White House.
The Post-Carter Administration Human Rights Work series is arranged into five subseries. The Human Rights Organizations subseries documents Derian's post-Carter administration human rights work in connection with various organizations, NGO's and research institutes. The Symposia and Conferences subseries comprises programs, proceedings, and papers presented at conferences and symposia attended by Derian. The General Files subseries contains subject files assembled by Derian that address broad human rights matters, including some materials on civil rights movement in Mississippi, human rights during the Reagan administration, and human rights violations around the world, including torture, murder, and kidnappings. The Prizes and Awards subseries covers the materials concerning Derian's work on committees of various foundations advocating the improvement of human rights conditions worldwide. The Miscellaneous Files subseries contains materials such as articles, dissertation monographs, reports, correspondence, political posters, and news clippings which refer to diverse issues such as humans rights and the Bush administration, the women's rights movement, U.S. foreign policy, and evaluation of the political and human rights situation in various Latin American countries.
Recordings of Patricia Derian's public speeches, interviews and excerpts from political protests in Argentina are housed in the Audiovisual Series. The Oversized Material grouping houses large items removed from files throughout the collection. Acquired as part of the Human Rights Archive at Duke University.
Related Material
Patricia Derian Papers (Chiefly civil rights material)
Special Collections Department, Mississippi State University Library
Marshall T. Meyer Papers (Human rights in Latin America and Middle East)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jimmy Carter Library and Museum
United States -- Foreign relations -- 1977-1981; Human Rights -- Latin America; Human rights movements -- Latin America; Human Rights -- Chile; Human Rights -- El Salvador; Civil rights movements -- United States; Human Rights -- Argentina; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1981-1989; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1989-1993; Videocassettes; Latin America -- Foreign relations -- United States; United States -- Military policy; Civil rights movements -- Mississippi -- History; United States -- Foreign relations -- Latin America; Women's rights -- United States; Women in public life -- United States; Audiocassettes; CD-ROMs; Machine-readable records; Posters; United States. Dept. of State. Bureau for Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs; United States. Dept. of State; Derian, Patricia M.; Human Rights Archive (Duke University); Carter, Jimmy, 1924-
- Carter Administration - 1980 Campaign and Employment Series, 1976-1982, 0.5 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Small series includes materials concerning the organization of the 1980 election campaign in which Derian served as Deputy Director, and assisted with recruitment of more minority and women campaigners. Also contains items documenting procedures for Derian's position in the White House. Folder titles are original.
  - 1980 Carter-Mondale campaign materials 1, 1976 and undated (Box 1)
  - 1980 Carter-Mondale campaign materials 2, 1976 and undated (Box 1)
  - 1980 Carter-Mondale campaign materials 3, 1976 and undated (Box 1)
  - State Department materials related to Derian's employment and position, 1977-1981 and undated (Box 1)
  - Patricia M. Derian background check, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Women Presidential appointees by the Carter Administration, 1979 July [poster, 19x29"] (Box 1)
- Department of State Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs Bureau Series, 1976-2008 and undated, 6 boxes
  Files pertaining to Derian's work as Assistant Secretary for Human Rights and Humanitarian affairs during the Carter administration, 1977-1981. Derian's files typically house correspondence, reports, speeches, and unclassified State Department documents. Arranged into two subseries: General Folders and Argentina. Files are in original order as received.
  - General Folders Subseries, 1976-1982 and undated
    Includes documents regarding the formation and restructuring of the Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs Bureau, weekly reports, interdepartmental and personal correspondence, memorabilia, unclassified State Department documents, Derian's speeches and interviews, and news clippings and other print material. Arranged in original order as received.
    - Memorabilia 1 - Correspondence, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
    - Memorabilia 2 - Assorted, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
    - Memorabilia 3 - News clippings, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
    - Poster, Somoza Bombs His Own People, 17x24", undated (Box 1)
    - Department of State documents, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - Weekly reports 1, 1979 Mar. 26 - Jun. 25 (Box 1)
    - Weekly reports 2, 1979 Jul 5 - Nov. 13 (Box 1)
    - Bureau of HR/HA restructuring, 1978-1979 and undated (Box 1)
    - Travel documents, 1977-1980, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Visa applications, 1977, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Congressional Record, 1977 Apr. 6 - 1978 Sept. 6. (Box 2)
    - Congressional Record, 1981, Sept. 10 (Separated In BOX Carter Adm. ½) (Box 2)
    - Cyrus Vance resignation, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Travel: 23rd International Conference of Red Cross, Bucharest, 1977 Oct. (Box 2)
    - Travel: NATO Ministerial Meeting, Brussels, 1977 Dec. 7-9 (Box 2)
    - Travel: UNCHR Executive Committee Session, Geneva, 1978 Oct. 9-11 (Box 2)
    - Interviews and speeches, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
    - Statements and testimonies, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
    - Congressional hearing: SFRC Senator Pell Subcommittee, 1979 Nov. 14 (Box 2)
    - News clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - News clippings, 1978 (Box 2)
    - News clippings, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Human rights related publications, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1, 1966-1980 and undated (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 2, 1980-1981 and undated (Box 3)
    - El Salvador correspondence, 1977-1981 and undated (Box 3)
    - Interdepartmental correspondence, 1977-1980, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Argentina Subseries, 1975-2008 and undated
    Folders assembled by Derian house materials that shed light on the making of United State's Argentine policy during the Carter administration and its aftermath. Items include unclassified State Department documents, correspondence, photographs and news clippings. Arranged in original order as received.
    - Argentina correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 4)
    - Chronology, 1975-1979 (Box 4)
    - Department of State documents, 1976-1980 and undated, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Department of State documents/excerpts, 1975-1982, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - List of Department of State documents, 1975-1982, 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Selected Department of State documents, 1976 (Box 4)
    - U.S. Congress Hearings on disappearances, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Interviews, 1977-1986 (Box 5)
    - Kissinger and Argentina, 1976-2004 and undated (Box 5)
    - Argentina 1985 trial, 1985 and undated (Box 5)
    - Military officers' confessions, 1995 and undated (Box 5)
    - Trials: Adolfo Scilingo (2003), Etchecolatz (2006), Simón (2006), 2003-2006 (Box 5)
    - Argentina photographs (Box 5)
    - Press releases, 1978-1995 (Box 5)
    - Derian's published articles, 1983 and undated (Box 5)
    - News clippings, 1976-2008 and undated, 8 folders (Box 5)
    - Operation Condor, undated (Box 5)
    - Witness to Truth: The Complicity of Church and Dictatorship in Argentina, 1976-1983, uncorrected, undated (Box 5)
    - Bound galley proofs, Emilio F. Mignone, undated (Box 5)
    - Research on Argentine junta, 1976-1982, 1979-2003 and undated (Box 5)
    - Argentina documents (Box 5)
    - Chapter manuscript, "The Carter Years," Iain Guest, undated (Box 6)
    - Coverage of Human Rights Abuses in the Buenos Aires Daily Press During Argentina's "Dirty War," 1976-1979: A Rule of Silence and its Exception, BA thesis by Kristin Anne Goss, 1987 (Box 6)
    - Screening of Prisoner without a Name, Cell without a Number, 1983 (Box 6)
    - National Security Archives (NSA) documents and events re: Argentina, 2002-2003 (Box 6)
- Post-Carter Administration Human Rights Work Series, 1978-2007 and undated, 8 boxes
  Files relating to Derian's human rights work following her position in the Carter administration. Arranged into five subseries: Human Rights Organizations, Symposia and Conferences, General Files, Prizes and Awards, and Miscellaneous Material. Folders are arranged in original order as received.
  Related material on specific countries or geographical areas also found in the Department of State Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs Bureau Series and the Countries Series.
  - Human Rights Organizations Subseries, 1978-2007
    Documents Derian's post-Carter administration human rights work in connection with various human rights organizations, NGO's and research institutes such as Human Rights Watch, Amnesty International, International Human Rights Council, Overseas Development Council, Southern Regional Council, Villiers Foundation, and Vietnam Memorial Association among others. The materials in this subseries includes correspondence, reports, articles and news clippings. Arranged in alphabetical order by organization.
    - American Civil Liberties Union, 2006-2007 (Box 7)
    - 20th Century Task Force on War Criminals, 1998 (Box 7)
    - Americas Watch, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Amnesty International, 1981-2003 (Box 7)
    - Carnegie Commission on Preventing Deadly Conflict, 1997 (Box 7)
    - Center For Policy Alternatives, 2000-2001 (Box 7)
    - Council on Foreign Relations I, 1978-1995 (Box 7)
    - Council on Foreign Relations II, 1996-2007 (Box 7)
    - Council on Foreign Relations III, undated (Box 7)
    - FSU Center for the Advancement of Human Rights, 2000-2001 (Box 7)
    - Human Rights Internet, 1981-1987 (Box 7)
    - International Human Rights Council, 1994 (Box 7)
    - International Human Rights Council, 1995 (Box 7)
    - International Human Rights Law Group, 1981-1989 (Box 7)
    - Korean Peace Foundation, 1995 (Box 7)
    - Overseas Development Council, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Southern Regional Council, 1981-2003 (Box 7)
    - International Negotiation Network, 1995 (Box 7)
    - Human Rights Watch
      - Food and sanctions, 1990 (Box 7)
      - Policies, 1993 (Box 7)
      - Food and medicine as weapons, 1991 and undated (Box 7)
      - Food and medicine as weapons, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Middle East Watch - 1990-1991 Iraq War, 1989-1991 and undated (Box 7)
    - Middle East Watch (Box 8)
      - Israel and Hyman bookbinder, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
      - Genocide and war crimes in Iraq, Israel and Chile, 1991-1993 (Box 8)
      - Israel and Palestine, 1988-1989 (Box 8)
      - Human rights in the Middle East 1980, 1987-1988 (Box 8)
      - ANERA (American Near East Relief Aid) Project, 1984 (Box 8)
      - ANERA Project, 1985-1988, 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Women's organizations in Egypt, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Vietnam Memorial Association (VMA)
      - Correspondence, undated (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1995-1998 (Box 8)
      - Expenses and trip reports, 1993 (Box 8)
      - Financial reports, 1995 (Box 8)
      - Embargo, 1993 (Box 8)
      - Receipts, 1993 (Box 8)
      - Articles, 1983-1999 (Box 8)
      - Contact List, 1993 (Box 8)
    - Villiers Foundation, 1981 (Box 8)
    - The World Bank Socialist Republic of Vietnam Primarily Education Project, 1993 (Box 8)
  - Symposia and Conferences Subseries, 1975-2004 and undated
    Comprises programs and proceedings of professional conferences and symposia which Patricia Derian attended between 1981 and 2004. Includes papers presented by Derian and others at these events. Arranged in original order as received.
    - Salzburg Seminars, 1996-2004 (Box 9)
    - Colloquium on Human Rights Policy and Law, SUNY Oct 1981, 1980-1981 and undated (Box 9)
    - U.S. Military Academy 33rd Annual Student Conference on United States Affairs Proceedings, 1981 Nov. 18-21 (Box 9)
    - Design Seminar, Mar. 1-12, 1981, 1981 and undated (Box 9)
    - Central America and the Politics of Hope: International Dimensions of the Crisis, 1985 Mar. 8-9, 1985 and undated (Box 9)
    - Alfred K. Lawenstein Symposium, UNC, 1983 Mar. 29-30, 1985 (Box 9)
    - Tough Jobs, Hard Choices: Careers in Public Service, JFK School of Government, Cambridge, 1987 Feb. 19 (Box 9)
    - The Jane Adams Conference on Security in the Nuclear Age, 1985-1987 (Box 9)
    - International Human Rights and U.S. Foreign Policy Symposium, Georgetown University, 1988 Dec. 8-10, 1988 and undated (Box 9)
    - National Democratic Institute International Visitors Program, Atlanta, 1988 Jul. 15-16, 1988 and undated (Box 9)
    - Theology, Politics and Peace, The Carter Presidential Center, Atlanta, 1988 Apr. 21-23, 1983-1988 and undated (Box 9)
    - Issues in Modern Diplomacy Seminar, Georgetown, 1989 Feb. 22, 1988-1989 (Box 9)
    - Hollywood and the American Conscience, American University, 1989 Apr. 10, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Colloquium on Human Rights and Civil Society in Latin America, National Humanities Center, 1993 May 1, 1993 and undated (Box 9)
    - Andrei Sakharov Symposium, Moscow, 1991 May 21-25, 1991 (Box 9)
    - Law, Culture, and Human Rights: Islamic Perspectives in the Contemporary World, Yale Law School, 1993 Nov. 5-6, 1993 and undated (Box 9)
    - Papers presented at the conference Law, Culture, and Human Rights: Islamic Perspectives in the Contemporary World, Yale Law School, 1993 Nov. 5-6 (Box 9)
    - Conference proceedings re: Human Rights in the Islamic and Arab World, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Deterring Humanitarian Law Violations: Strengthening Enforcement, University of Virginia, 1994 Nov. 4-5, 1994 (Box 9)
    - Conference of Asian Democrats, Korea, 1994 (Box 9)
    - Conference of Asian Democrats Schedule, Korea, 1994 (Box 9)
    - Conference on International Terrorism, Warwick, Nov 4-6, 1983 and undated (Box 10)
    - United States Institute of Peace Panel Discussion Mar. 2004, 1994 and undated. (Box 10)
    - Islam and Christianity at the Threshold of the 21st Century, Carnegie, 1995 Feb. 9 (Box 10)
    - Action Council for Peace in the Balkans, Apr. 1995, 1995 and undated (Box 10)
    - International Intervention for the Cause of Human Rights, LBJ Library, 1995 Mar. 3, 1993-1995 and undated (Box 10)
    - International Human Rights and Feminism, the Lotos Club, NYC, 1988 Nov. 18, 1988 and undated (Box 10)
    - NCNW International Seminar: paper and drafts, 1975 and undated (Box 10)
  - General Files Subseries, 1962-2007
    Derian assembled these subject files on topics such as civil rights in the U.S., the civil rights movement in Mississippi, international efforts for the trial of war criminals, terrorism, and human rights policies of the Carter and Reagan administrations. Folders typically contain Derian's personal notes, correspondence, articles, interviews, reports, and news clippings. Between the years 1981 and 2004 Patricia Derian also served on the award-giving committees of various foundations advocating the improvement of human rights conditions worldwide, such as the Carter-Menil Human Rights Foundation and Robert F. Kennedy Memorial Foundation. Arranged in original order as received.
    - Human rights evolve, 1989-2003 and undated (Box 11)
    - Civil rights: general, 1980-2003 and undated (Box 11)
    - Civil rights: Mississippi Sovereignty Commission report on Patricia Derian, 1966-1997 and undated (Box 11)
    - Civil rights: Patricia Derian materials, 1962-2002 and undated (Box 11)
    - Civil rights: Mississippi articles, 1962-2004 (Box 11)
    - Violations, 1983-2003 and undated (Box 11)
    - Torture, 1983-2007 and undated (Box 11)
    - Terrorism, 1985 (Box 11)
    - Journalism, 2003 (Box 11)
    - Prisons, 2002-2007 and undated (Box 11)
    - War criminals and justice, 1983-2006 and undated (Box 11)
    - International Criminal Court, 1988-2003 and undated (Box 11)
    - Defending Carter administration, 1978-2001 and undated (Box 11)
    - Carter Presidential Museum Human Rights Gallery, undated (Box 11)
    - Human rights in Reagan administration - correspondence, 1981-1988 (Box 11)
    - Human rights in Reagan administration - articles, 1981-1988 (Box 11)
    - Human rights in Reagan administration - documents, notes, interviews, 1980-1982 and undated (Box 11)
    - Human rights in Reagan administration - Iran Contra, 1981-1984 (Box 11)
    - Jim Langford - New Ideas, 1995-1997 and undated (Box 12)
    - U.N. multilateral treaties, 1948-1999 (Box 12)
    - Human rights as foreign policy, 1976-1992 and undated (Box 12)
    - General human rights materials, 1984-2003 and undated (Box 12)
    - Human rights documents, 1977 (Box 12)
    - Names compiled by Patricia Derian, 1981-2003 (Box 12)
    - The Interdependent Interview, 1982 (Box 12)
  - Prizes and Awards Subseries, 1981-2004